Guide to the Stanford University Entomological Collection
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University entomological collection
1891-1929
SC0515
Stanford University
0.75 Linear feet
Records concern the collection of insects used in the teaching of entomology at Stanford and include two record books listing the individual lots of insects with collector and location noted and a small amount of related correspondence. Many of the specimens were taken on the grounds of the campus and in nearby communities, but there are also specimens from other states, Brazil, Japan, the Galapagos Islands and other locations. The first volume includes a note on the early collectors. Persons represented in the record books include Profs. Vernon L. Kellogg, Robert W. Doane, Clelia D. Mosher, William Russell Dudley, R. E. Snodgrass, William A. Snow, John C. Branner, and Isabel McCracken. Correspondents include William M. Mann, James G. Needham, A. L. Melander, John M. Aldrich, William L. Holt, John M. Miller, George F. Nuttall, Lawrence Bruner, L. O. Howard, and W. M. Wheeler.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1970.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Description of the Collection
Records concern the collection of insects used in the teaching of entomology at Stanford and include two record books listing the individual lots of insects with collector and location noted and a small amount of related correspondence. Many of the specimens were taken on the grounds of the campus and in nearby communities, but there are also specimens from other states, Brazil, Japan, the Galapagos Islands and other locations. The first volume includes a note on the early collectors. Persons represented in the record books include Profs. Vernon L. Kellogg, Robert W. Doane, Clelia D. Mosher, William Russell Dudley, R. E. Snodgrass, William A. Snow, John C. Branner, and Isabel McCracken. Correspondents include William M. Mann, James G. Needham, A. L. Melander, John M. Aldrich, William L. Holt, John M. Miller, George F. Nuttall, Lawrence Bruner, L. O. Howard, and W. M. Wheeler.
Access Terms
Aldrich, John Merton, 1866-1934.; Branner, John Casper, 1850-1922.; Bruner, Lawrence.; Dudley, William Russel, 1849-1911; Greeley, Arthur White.; Henshaw, Samuel, 1852-1941.; Howard, L. O. (Leland Ossian), 1857-1950.; Kellogg, Vernon L. (Vernon Lyman), 1867-1937.; Mann, William M., 1886-1960.; McCracken, Isabel.; Melander, Axel Leonard, 1878-; Mosher, Clelia Duel, 1863-1940; Needham, James G. (James George), 1868-1956.; Nuttall, George Henry Falkiner, 1862-1937.; Scudder, SAmuel Hubbard, 1837-1911.; Snow, William Appleton, d. 1900.; Wheeler, William Morton, 1865-1937.; Entomology.; Insects.
Collection Contents
- Entomological collection
  - Record book of insect lots No. 1 - No. 428, 1891 - 1902 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    See pages 23-25 for notes on the early collectors
  - Record book of insect lots No. 429 to No. 610, 1902 - 1925 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Pages 1-19 contain notes on a few lots from the first volume
  - Aldrich, J. M., 1907, letter to [Robert W.] Doane (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bartruff, Mary M., 1896, letter to Vernon S. Kellog re identification of insect (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bruner, Lawrence (Univ. of Nebraska), 1896, letter to Vernon S. Kellogg re specimens (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Douglas, Lenard, 1902, letter to O. P. Jenkins re identification of moths (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Greeley, Arthur W., 1899, letter to Vernon S. Kellogg re lot no. 220 (Brazilian butterflies) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Henshaw, Samuel, 1898, letter to W. A. Snow re Guadalupe beetles (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Holt, William L., 1912, letter to Vernon Kellogg re European butterflies he's sending (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Howard, L.O. (U. S. Dept. of Agriculture), 1906 to Vernon S. Kellogg re specimen (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Mann, William M. (Harvard), 1912, letters to Vernon S. Kellogg and Robert W. Doane re specimens of Brazilian butterflies with lists (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Melander, A.L. (State College at Washington), 1910, letter to G. Pemberton re specimens (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miller, John M. (U.S. Dept. of Agriculture), 1907 letter to Vernon L. Kellogg (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Needham, James G. (Cornell), 1897 letter to re specimens (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Nuttall, George H. F., 1908 letter to re lot no. 530 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Plank, F., Jr., 1894 letter to David S. Jordan re lot no. 23 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Scudder, H. S., 1897 letter re lot no. 186 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Wheeler, W. M. (American Museum of Natural History), 1904 letter to re his research (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Letters to Dr. Isabelle McCracken, 1929 re specimens (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous items (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Note on lot no. 19 (Edward Hyatt) (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Note on lot no. 60 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Note on lot no. 116 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Note on lot no. 201 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Note on lot no. 371 (1901) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Note on lot no. 492 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Note on lot no. 517 (J. C. Branner) (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Note on lot no. 524 (Box 2, Folder 26)